<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Account of the proceedings against the rioters at Guild-Hall on Midsummer-Day, 1682 with the judgment past upon them at the Court of Kings-Bench, Westminster, on Tuesday, the 26th of June, 1683.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25678</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A352</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8266</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11644039</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11644039</idno>
            <idno type="VID">47968</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25678)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 47968)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 3:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Account of the proceedings against the rioters at Guild-Hall on Midsummer-Day, 1682 with the judgment past upon them at the Court of Kings-Bench, Westminster, on Tuesday, the 26th of June, 1683.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet (2 p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by George Croom ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Trials (Riots) --  England --  London.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:47968:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>AN ACCOUNT OF THE PROCEEDINGS AGAINST THE RIOTERS AT GUILD-HALL: ON <hi>Midſummer-Day,</hi> 1682. With the Judgment paſt upon them at the Court of <hi>Kings-Bench Weſtminſter,</hi> on <hi>Tueſday</hi> the 26th of <hi>June,</hi> 1683.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas an Information againſt the Lord <hi>Gray</hi> of <hi>Warke,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Player,</hi> Alderman <hi>Corniſh, Thomas Pilkington, Samuel Shute,</hi> and <hi>Slingsby Bethel,</hi> Eſquires; Mr. <hi>Jinkes,</hi> Mr. <hi>Jeakell,</hi> Mr. <hi>Goodenough,</hi> Mr. <hi>Freeman,</hi> Mr. <hi>Deagle,</hi> Mr. <hi>Wickham,</hi> Mr. <hi>Swinnocke,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Keys</hi> came to be Tryed in <hi>Eaſter</hi> Term laſt, at <hi>Guild-Hall,</hi> before the Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Saunders</hi> for a Ryot, by them committed at the Election of Sheriffs on <hi>Midſummer day</hi> laſt, and the ſaid Perſons thereof found Guilty, That when it was expected Judgment ſhould have been given againſt them on the laſt day of the ſaid Term, part of the ſaid Perſons appearing by their Counſel moved in Arreſt of Judgment entring ſeverally into a Recognizance of 500 <hi>l.</hi> to appear the firſt day of this Term, at the Court of <hi>Kings-Bench, Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> which they doing accordingly, their Appearances were then Recorded. But the hearing what their Counſel had to offer by way of Exceptions, why Judgment ſhould not paſs upon them purſuant to the late Verdict, was put off till <hi>Fryday</hi> the 15th, and from thence to <hi>Tueſday</hi> the 19th, of this preſent <hi>June,</hi> on which day a Motion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made for the Judgment of the Court upon the ſaid Perſons, ſeveral things were urged by their Counſel, as Exceptions againſt the Verdict, relating to the Award of the <hi>Venire</hi> for return of the Jury to Try that Information: alſo one of their Counſel urged, That they having been lawfully Aſſembled could not commit a Ryot, or be Guilty of the Aſſault upon the Lord Mayor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but that the Perſons only that made ſuch Aſſault were Guilty. Very much was ſaid in their behalf, ſix Counſellors ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for them one after another, after which the kings Counſel anſwered all thoſe Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections and continued to pray Judgment, by having the Fines ſet upon them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:47968:2"/>
            <p>The Court then delivered their Senſe of what had been ſaid, and were of Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nothing urged by way of Exceptions had validity enough in it to hinder Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; particularly taking notice it was a new Argument, that maintained a Ryot could not be committed where perſons were lawfully Aſſembled: It being aſk'd by way of Anſwer, If many People were lawfully Aſſembled at Church for Religious Worſhip, and there roſe in a Tumult and pull'd down the Church, or uſed other violence, Whether it would not be a Ryot, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But one of the Judges being ſomewhat Indiſpoſed; alſo the hearing of Affidavits, on both ſides, like to be long, the Matter was further put off till <hi>Wedneſday</hi> the 20th of <hi>June</hi> inſtant.</p>
            <p>On which ſaid 20th of <hi>June,</hi> there being hopes that one of the Judges, who was then ſick, did recover and would in a few days be able to come to <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> (there being only two Judges upon the Bench) and for ſome other Reaſons, it was a fourth time put off to <hi>Munday</hi> the 25th of the ſame Moneth. But the ſaid <hi>Judge</hi> not being ſo recovered as was hoped as alſo on the ſaid 25th day one of the two <hi>Judges</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned being likewiſe very much indiſpoſed in his health it was a fifth time put off, but ordered to be moved again the next day in hopes he might then be better.</p>
            <p>Accordingly on <hi>Tueſday, the 26th of June,</hi> 1683. It was the laſt time moved and the Judgment of the Court prayed againſt them. Eleven of the ſaid-Ryoters being preſent in Court, and only three, <hi>viz.</hi> The Lord <hi>Gray, Mr Keyes</hi> and <hi>Richard Goodenough</hi> wanting.</p>
            <p>The <hi>ſix Counſellers</hi> at Law herein already mentioned ſeverally uſing what arguments they could to Moderate and make eaſy the Fines. But the <hi>Kings Councel</hi> very eaſily anſwered all their Objections and appealed to them all to produce any one Preſident that ever the Sheriffs of <hi>London,</hi> had the ſuperiority of the Lord Mayor. That in Mr. <hi>Bethel</hi>'s time when all theſe diſorders took their beginning yet then Sir <hi>Robert Clayton,</hi> being Lord Mayor, reſerved the power of adjourning the Common Hall as appeared at the Trial, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In concluſion after much ſaid on both ſides and that the Court had ſeverally given their opinions they proceeded to Judgment and Impoſed upon the ſaid perſons the Fines following.</p>
            <p>Firſt, upon Mr. <hi>Pilkinton</hi> the Court were ſo favourable by reaſon of his preſent Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, &amp;c. to Impoſe only five hundred Pounds (or five hundred Marks) upon Mr. <hi>Shute</hi> one thouſand Marks, upon the Lord <hi>Gray</hi> one thouſand Pounds (or a thouſand Marks) upon <hi>Alderman Corniſh</hi> one thouſand Marks, upon Mr. <hi>Bethel,</hi> one thouſand Marks, upon Sir <hi>Thomas Player</hi> five hundred Marks, upon Mr. <hi>Jinks</hi> three hundred Marks, upon Mr. <hi>Deagle</hi> four hundred Marks upon <hi>Richard Freeman</hi> three hundred Marks, upon <hi>Richard Goodenough</hi> five hundred Marks, upon Mr. <hi>Keyes</hi> one hundred Marks, upon Mr. <hi>Wickham,</hi> one hundred Marks, and upon Mr. <hi>Swinnock</hi> five hundred Marks. Several of them were Ordered alſo to ſtand committed until the ſaid fines ſhall be paid.</p>
            <p>It is Obſervable that before each of the ſaid Perſons were fin'd, ſuch of them as were in Court, ſpoke alſo ſeverally for themſelves. Some by way of Excuſe that that they did not ſtay longer at <hi>Guild Hall,</hi> but till they Poled, others, that they were not at the Hall the day when the Riot was Committed, ſome that they had but ſmall Eſtates, and were not ſo Rich as the Kings Counſel affirmed, one of them th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> he had ſpent much of his Eſtate in the Kings Service, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> All which Particulars were likewiſe Conſidered by the Court.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>George Croom,</hi> in <hi>Thames-ſtreet,</hi> over againſt <hi>Baynard</hi>'s <hi>Caſtle,</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
